<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Copyright 2023 Michal Kosciesza -->
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>net.mkiol.SpeechNote</id>
  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>MPL-2.0</project_license>
  <developer_name>Michal Kosciesza</developer_name>
  <name>Speech Note</name>
  <summary>Note taking, reading and translating with Speech to Text, Text to Speech and Machine Translation</summary>
  <description>
    <p>Speech Note let you take, read and translate notes in multiple languages.
      It uses Speech to Text, Text to Speech and Machine Translation to do so.
      Text and voice processing take place entirely offline, locally on your
      computer, without using a network connection. Your privacy is always
      respected. No data is sent to the Internet.</p>
  </description>
  <categories>
    <category>AudioVideo</category>
  </categories>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>speech</keyword>
    <keyword>voice</keyword>
    <keyword>stt</keyword>
    <keyword>asr</keyword>
    <keyword>tts</keyword>
    <keyword>nmt</keyword>
    <keyword>translator</keyword>
    <keyword>deepspeech</keyword>
    <keyword>vosk</keyword>
    <keyword>whisper</keyword>
    <keyword>rhvoice</keyword>
    <keyword>piper</keyword>
    <keyword>espeak</keyword>
    <keyword>mbrola</keyword>
    <keyword>coqui</keyword>
    <keyword>offline</keyword>
    <keyword>bergamot</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <caption>Speech Note main window</caption>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/mkiol/dsnote/main/desktop/screenshots/speechnote-screenshot-fullscreen.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Notepad mode</caption>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/mkiol/dsnote/main/desktop/screenshots/speechnote-screenshot-light-notepad.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Translator mode (dark theme)</caption>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/mkiol/dsnote/main/desktop/screenshots/speechnote-screenshot-dark-translator.png</image>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <caption>Translator mode on Plasma Mobile</caption>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/mkiol/dsnote/main/desktop/screenshots/speechnote-screenshot-mobile-translator.png</image>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>
  <url type="homepage">https://github.com/mkiol/dsnote</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/mkiol/dsnote/issues</url>
  <url type="translate">https://app.transifex.com/mkiol/dsnote</url>
  <update_contact>dsnote_AT_mkiol.net</update_contact>
  <launchable type="desktop-id">net.mkiol.SpeechNote.desktop</launchable>
  <content_rating type="oars-1.1" />
  <releases>
    <release version="4.1.0" date="2023-08-19">
      <description>
      <p>Speech to Text:</p>
      <ul>
      <li>Support for GPU acceleration for Whisper models.
          If a suitable GPU device is found in the system, it will be used to accelerate processing.
          This significantly reduces the time of decoding (usually 2 times or more).
          GPU hardware acceleration is not enabled by default. Use the option in <i>Settings</i> to turn it on.
          Disable, if you observe any problems when using Speech to Text with Whisper models.
      </li>
      <li>Fix: Whisper model wasn't able to decode short speech sentences.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Text to Speech:</p>
      <ul>
      <li>Option <i>Speech speed</i> in <i>Settings</i> to make synthesized speech slower or faster.</li>
      <li>New models from Massively Multilingual Speech (MMS) project.
          MMS project released models for 1100 languages, but only the following have been enabled:
          Albanian, Amharic, Arabic, Basque, Bengali, Bulgarian, Chinese, Greek, Hindi, Icelandic, Indonesian,
          Kazakh, Korean, Latin, Latvian, Malay, Mongolian, Polish, Portuguese, Swahili, Tagalog, Tatar, Thai,
          Turkish, Uzbek, Vietnamese and Yoruba.
          If you would like any other MMS model to be included, please let us know.</li>
      <li>New Coqui voices for: Japanese, Turkish and Spanish.</li>
      <li>New Piper voices for: Czech, German, Hungarian, Portuguese and Slovak.</li>
      <li>Update of RHVoice voices for Slovak and Czech.</li>
      </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="4.0.0" date="2023-08-07">
      <description>
      <p>Translator:</p>
      <ul>
      <li>Support for offline translations between following languages: Catalan, Bulgarian, Czech, Danish
      English, Spanish, German, Estonian, French, Italian, Polish, Portuguese, Norwegian, Iranian, Dutch,
      Russian, Ukrainian, Icelandic.</li>
      <li>Translator uses models that were created as part of Bergamot project.</li>
      <li>To switch between Notepad and Translator modes, use the toggle buttons in the upper right corner.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Interface:</p>
      <ul>
      <li>User interface has been redesign. It is more handy and better supports portrait view for mobile.</li>
      <li>Settings option to force specific interface style has been added. It is useful to overcome UI glitches when app is running under GNOME desktop environment.</li>
      <li>Application has been translated to new languages: Dutch and Italian.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Text to Speech:</p>
      <ul>
      <li>All existing Piper models have been updated.</li>
      <li>New Piper voices for: English, Swedish, Turkish, Polish, German, Spanish, Finnish, French, Ukrainian, Russian,
            Swahili, Serbian, Romanian, Luxembourgish and Georgian.</li>
      <li>New RHVoice model for Slovak language</li>
      </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="3.1.5" date="2023-07-06">
      <description>
        <p>Text to Speech:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>New Coqui voice for English: Jenny</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Speech to Text:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Quicker decoding when using DeepSpeech/Coqui models (especially on ARM CPU)</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="3.1.4" date="2023-07-03">
      <description>
        <p>Interface:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Option to show recent changes in the app (About -> Changes)</li>
        <li>French translation update (Many thanks to L'Africain)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Text to Speech:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>New Piper model for Chinese</li>
        <li>New RHVoice model for Uzbek</li>
        <li>Updated RHVoice models for Ukrainian</li>
        <li>Piper and RHVoice engines updated to most recent versions</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Speech to Text:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Whisper 'Large' models enabled for all languages</li>
        <li>Whisper supported on older CPUs (i.e. without AVX/AVX2 extensions)</li>
        <li>Whisper engine update (20% performance improvement, 50% less memory)</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="3.1.3" date="2023-06-24">
      <description>
        <p>Text to Speech:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>New Piper models for: Icelandic, Swedish and Russian</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Speech to Text:</p>
        <ul>
        <li>Whisper fine-tuned models for: Czech, Slovak, Slovenian, Romanian, Russian, Hungarian and Polish</li>
        <li>Standard Whisper models enabled also for:
            Amharic, Arabic, Bengali, Danish, Estonian, Basque, Persian, Hindi,
            Croatian, Hungarian, Icelandic, Georgian,
            Kazakh, Korean, Lithuanian, Latvian, Mongolian,
            Maltese, Nepali, Romanian, Slovak, Slovenian, Albanian,
            Swahili, Tagalog, Tatar, Uzbek and Yoruba</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="3.1.2" date="2023-06-20">
      <description>
        <ul>
        <li>Fix: Whisper STT didn't work for Chinese language</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="3.1.1" date="2023-06-17">
      <description>
        <ul>
        <li>Text to Speech: New DeepSpeech model for Latvain</li>
        <li>Minor UI improvements</li>
        <li>Fix: Crash during Text to Speech on some systems</li>
        <li>Fix: Downloaded models disappeared after app restart when Downloads directory was not set in the system</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="3.1.0" date="2023-06-13" />
  </releases>
</component>
